{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A man who claimed allegiance to this colony despite living in one to its north prompted mob violence that became known as Cresap’s War. The leader of this colony petitioned Queen Anne after another colony was granted land below the 40th parallel. After Richard Ingle and William Claiborne took control of this colony, Jesuit priests were sent back to England during the \"Plundering Time.\" For ten points, name this colony, whose first Proprietary-Governor was Leonard Calvert.",
      "answer": "Maryland"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Calutron was made as part of this project for use with the Y-12 Project. Personnel of this project worked throughout Europe in Operation Alsos. For this project, Kenneth Nichols negotiated with the Eldorado Gold Mines and the Union Miniere [[meen- YEHR]] du Haut-Katanga which ran the Shinkolobwe [[sheen-koh-LOH-bweh]] Mine in Belgian Congo. This project created the Thin Man gun-type design. Leslie Groves and Robert Oppenheimer directed this project, which had sites in Oak Ridge and Los Alamos. For ten points, name this project which produced the first atomic bomb.",
      "answer": [
        "Manhattan Project",
        "Development of Substitute Materials"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "While mayor, this politician implemented the Care Not Cash initiative to expand housing options. This politician led the Parking and Traffic Commission under Willie Brown. This man came under fire for hosting a birthday party at the French Laundry restaurant amid COVID-19. This man oversaw the cessation of executions at San Quentin Prison and appointed the first inspector general of his state’s BART transit system. For ten points, name this man who was elected governor of California in 2018.",
      "answer": "Gavin Newsom"
    },
    {
      "question": "Under this king, Peter de la Mare was chosen as speaker. Both the Good and Bad Parliaments operated under this king, whom William of Wykeham [[WIK-um]] helped develop Windsor Castle. The \"Lady of the Sun,\" Alice Perrers [[peh-REHR]], had an affair with this ruler. This ruler rose to power after removing Roger Mortimer and formed the Order of the Garter in 1348. This king, whose son was the Black Prince, won at Crécy and Poitiers [[pwah-TYEH]] against France. For ten points, name this English king who began the Hundred Years' War.",
      "answer": [
        "Edward III",
        "Edward of Windsor before mentioned 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 8"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. Frank “Big Black” Smith was tortured during one of these events, which was led in part by Weather Underground member Sam Melville. That example of these events was sparked by the killing of George Jackson. Participants in one of these events took control of the \"D Yard,\" which led Nelson Rockefeller to call in the National Guard. For ten points, name this type of event which occurred in September 1971 at Attica Correctional Facility, involving an uprising of over 2,200 inmates.",
      "answer": [
        "Prison Riot",
        "synonyms for Prison such as Penitentiary",
        "Jail",
        "synonyms for riot such as uprising"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "While working for this institution, Frank Hartman invented the liquid oxygen tent. This place was the first of its kind to implement the closed staff system. A painting set in this place contains a snail as well as a red ribbon representing an umbilical cord and was created by Frida Kahlo following a miscarriage. A home near this location named for its founder's wife, Clara, housed nursing students. For ten points, name this Detroit medical institution named for an automobile business magnate.",
      "answer": [
        "Henry Ford Hospital",
        "HFH"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Since its rediscovery in 1849, the exploits of the eponymous hero of this poem and his hairy friend, Enkidu, across ancient Iraq have been referenced in many forms of media from Philip Roth’s The Great American Novel to the video game Civilization. The hero of this poem visits Utnapishtim, who recounts a story of how he survived a global flood by building a giant boat from reeds. Found in Nineveh by Austen Henry Layard, this poem was originally written on twelve cuneiform tablets. For ten points, what is the name of this Sumerian epic poem?",
      "answer": "The Epic of Gilgamesh"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this country, a march on Sonsonate [[sohn-soh-NAH-teh]] was organized by Feliciano Ama. A neighbor targeted this country’s Ilopango airbase during a war named for its hundred hour length. An activist in this country named Farabundo Martí lends his name to its FMLN party. In this country, Roberto D'Aubuisson [[doh-bwee-SOHN]], who founded the ARENA party, may have ordered the killing of Bishop Óscar Romero. The Football War was fought between this country and its northeastern neighbor, Honduras. For ten points, name this Central American country which fought a thirteen-year Civil War.",
      "answer": [
        "Republic of El Salvador",
        "República de El Salvador 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 8"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A line of defense named for this man stretched from the Baltic Sea to the Carpathians. Maxim Litvinov was replaced by this man, who was ordered to purge a ministry of Jews. Georgy Malenkov and this man teamed up against Nikita Khrushchev in the failed Anti-Party Group takeover. This man secretly planned to partition Poland in a pact he signed with Joachim von Ribbentrop. The foreign minister for Joseph Stalin, for ten points, who was this man who names a type of improvised explosive known as his \"cocktail\"?",
      "answer": "Vyacheslav Molotov"
    },
    {
      "question": "While working for this publication, Janet Cooke won a Pulitzer Prize for her story about an eight-year-old heroin addict named Jimmy, though it was later revealed that the story was largely a fabrication. Under the editorship of Ben Bradlee, this publication published a series of documents detailing U.S. involvement in Southeast Asia. Jeff Bezos purchased this newspaper in 2013 for $250 million. For ten points, name this newspaper which published the Pentagon Papers after the New York Times was barred from doing so.",
      "answer": [
        "The Washington Post",
        "WaPo"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An 1870 disaster affecting this company may have inspired a P.G. Wodehouse novel sold in the U.S. as Three Men and a Maid. A trio of particularly large entities designed for this company was created by Harland and Wolff. Edward Smith was employed by this company, which was bought out by their rival, Cunard. Based in Liverpool, this company's best known asset was discovered by the archaeologist Robert Ballard many decades after it met its demise in 1912. For ten points, name this ocean liner company which owned the Titanic.",
        "answer": "White Star Line or Oceanic Steam Navigation Company"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This fleet mate of the Titanic was serving as a hospital ship when it was damaged by a German mine in 1916, but 1035 of the 1065 people on board survived its sinking.",
        "answer": "HMHS Britannic"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ash Upson ghostwrote a story about this man's best known action. Carl Adamson’s refusal to purchase an additional 600 goats that were allegedly left out of a count prevented this man from breaking a lease and set off a series of events resulting in his death, perhaps at the hands of Jesse Brazel. After losing a state senate race, this man joined the Texas Rangers and earlier served as Lincoln County sheriff, in which capacity he visited an acquaintance of Pete Maxwell who asked “Who is It?” For ten points, name this lawman who shot Billy the Kid.",
        "answer": "Pat Garrett"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Pat Garrett was one of Teddy Roosevelt's three \"White House Gunfighters\" with Ben Daniels and this Dodge City sheriff and gambler, who became a New York sports writer and is often depicted in media wearing a distinctive derby hat.",
        "answer": "Bat Masterson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Hackers targeted this state-owned company in 2012 with the Shamoon virus, possibly in retaliation for the U.S.'s involvement in Stuxnet. A 2019 drone attack conducted by Houthi rebels targeted two of this company's plants, disrupting global crude output by five percent. Months later, this company held an IPO on the Tadawul stock exchange with an estimated market cap of $1.88 trillion. For ten points, name this state-owned oil company of a certain Middle Eastern kingdom.",
        "answer": "Saudi Aramco"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1950, this Saudi king, known in the West as Ibn Saud, threatened nationalization of oil facilities in his country, thus forcing Aramco to agree to a 50/50 profit-sharing arrangement.",
        "answer": "Abdulaziz of Saudi Arabia or Abdulaziz bin Abdul Rahman Al Saud 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 8"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This mountain range's Rockfish Gap was the site of a Mountain Top Tavern meeting attended by John Marshall and Thomas Jefferson at which they discussed founding a university. A railroad named for this mountain range aimed to connect Piedmont with the Shenandoah Valley. Following the Indian Removal Act, many Cherokee hid on lands in this mountain range, which became Great Smoky Mountains National Park. Part of the Appalachians, for ten points, what is this colorfully named range?",
        "answer": "Blue Ridge Mountains"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the Smoky Mountains National Park was authorized in 1926, $5 million for its development was contributed by this former director of Standard Oil, the son of one of the company's co-founders.",
        "answer": "John D. Rockefeller, Jr."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author likely drew inspiration from the surgeon Joseph Bell for one of his characters, who tracks down ex-KKK members in the story “Five Orange Pips.\" Jefferson Hope offers two pills, one of which is poisoned, to two enemies in a novel by this author, the first of four full-length novels to feature this author's best known character. A cab driver is tracked down by the Baker Street Irregulars in a book by, for ten points, what author, whose novel A Study in Scarlet features the detective Sherlock Holmes?",
        "answer": "Arthur Conan Doyle"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In A Study in Scarlet, Dr. Watson reveals that he was injured while serving with the British army during the second Anglo war against an emirate from this country.",
        "answer": [
          "Islamic Republic of Afghanistan",
          "Emirate of Afghanistan"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After a show of force against this man, Abdel Haris Nasution [[NAH-SOO-TYOHN]] was suspended from service. The 30 September Movement occurred during this man's administration, during which several of this man's generals were killed under the orders of his future successor. This man established a \"Guided Democracy\" to bring political stability to his country and, assisted by his vice-president, Mohammad Hatta, implemented a set of national values called Pancasila [[pahn-chah-SEE-lah]]. For ten points, name this first president of Indonesia.",
        "answer": [
          "Sukarno or Kusno Sosrodihardjo",
          "Bung Karno",
          "Pak Karno",
          "Achmad Sukarno"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Sukarno hailed from this southernmost of the Greater Sunda Islands, the world's most populous island.",
        "answer": [
          "Java",
          "Jawa 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 8"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This is the official nickname of one location, former nicknames of which referenced its vast amounts of hog and hominy and a river known by Native Americans as “Big Bend.” An event that inspired this nickname was partially fueled by the death of Davy Crockett. That event which may have inspired this nickname involved 30,000 individuals responding to James K. Polk’s call for 2,600 troops during the Mexican-American War. For ten points, give this state nickname indicating the non-mandatory provision of armed forces from cities like Nashville.",
        "answer": "The Volunteer State"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The call for volunteers from Tennessee came not only from President Polk but also from this former Tennessee governor who had moved to Texas in 1832.",
        "answer": "Sam Houston"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this period, Louis Marie Turreau [[too-ROH]] used the “Infernal Columns'' tactic in the War in the Vendée [[vahn-DEH]]. At the height of this period, Jean-Baptiste Carrier [[kah-ree-YEH]] facilitated the death of former magistrates and members of the Catholic church in the Drowning at Nantes [[NAHNT]]. This period was ended by the Thermidorian Reaction, which included the ousting of the Committee of Public Safety. For ten points, name this tumultuous period of the French Revolution, known for mass executions of political opponents by guillotine.",
        "answer": [
          "Reign of Terror",
          "La Grande Terreur"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the late Napoleonic era, the people of the Vendée openly supported this monarch, who ruled for a decade after the fall of Napoleon before his replacement by Charles X.",
        "answer": [
          "Louis XVIII",
          "Louis the Desired",
          "or Louis le Désiré"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Settlements in the Americas",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "First permanent English settlement in the Americas, led by John Smith and Thomas Gates.",
          "answer": "Jamestown"
        },
        {
          "question": "Legendary disembarkation site of William Bradford, the Mayflower, and 130 Pilgrims.",
          "answer": "Plymouth Rock"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lost North Carolina colony founded by Sir Walter Raleigh.",
          "answer": "Roanoke"
        },
        {
          "question": "Florida city that is the oldest continuously inhabited European settlement in the U.S.",
          "answer": "St. Augustine"
        },
        {
          "question": "American colony led by Director-General Peter Stuyvesant in the 17th century.",
          "answer": [
            "New Netherland",
            "Nova Belgica",
            "Nieuw Nederland",
            "Novum Belgium"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Patron saint of animals, merchants, and ecology for which Santa Fe, New Mexico was named.",
          "answer": "Saint Francis of Assisi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Legendary Welsh prince said to have settled near the Mississippi River in the 12th century.",
          "answer": "Madoc or Madog, ab Owain Gwynedd"
        },
        {
          "question": "South Carolina location, the first European settlement in what became the continental U.S. in 1526.",
          "answer": "San Miguel de Guadalpe 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 8"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Golden Horde",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Grand Duchy in Russia that escaped the \"Tatar Yoke.\"",
          "answer": [
            "Moscow",
            "Muscovy",
            "Muscovite Russia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Grandson of Genghis Khan who founded the Golden Horde.",
          "answer": "Batu Khan or Tsar Batu"
        },
        {
          "question": "Italian republic given the city of Caffa by the Golden Horde.",
          "answer": "Genoa or Genova"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mongol territories that bordered the Golden Horde to the south.",
          "answer": [
            "Ilkhanate or Hülegü Ulus",
            "Iranzamin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Primary language of the Golden Horde.",
          "answer": [
            "Kipchak",
            "Northwestern Turkic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of the Golden Horde.",
          "answer": "Sarai"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle where Jalal ad-Din helped Lithuania defeat the Teutonic Order.",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Grunwald",
            "Battle of Žalgiris",
            "First Battle of Tannenberg"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Khanate, the last remnant of the Golden Horde, that survived until 1847.",
          "answer": "Kazakh Khanate 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 8"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Latin American Wars of Independence",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"Liberator\" who freed his native Venezuela, along with other Andean nations, from Spain.",
          "answer": "Simon Bolívar"
        },
        {
          "question": "19th-century state founded by that leader, who served as its first president.",
          "answer": "Gran Colombia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Argentine general and \"Protector of Peru\" who liberated the former provinces of Rio de la Plata.",
          "answer": "José de San Martín"
        },
        {
          "question": "President of Peru and Bolivia who names one of the latter nation's two capitals.",
          "answer": "Antonio José de Sucre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conference in an Ecuadorian city to discuss the future of independent states of South America.",
          "answer": "Guayaquil Conference or Conferencia de Guayaquil"
        },
        {
          "question": "1813 campaign which freed multiple states of Venezuela from Royalist control.",
          "answer": [
            "Admirable Campaign",
            "Campaña Admirable"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Spanish king whose 1810 abdication led to the May Revolutions, an early series of uprisings in South America.",
          "answer": [
            "Ferdinand VII of Spain",
            "Fernando VII",
            "Fernando el Deseado",
            "Ferdinand the Desired"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British earl and mercenary who oversaw the construction of the Chilean navy.",
          "answer": [
            "Thomas Cochrane",
            "the Earl of Dundonald 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 8"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An insurrection in this town was started by Tomás Romero and Pablo Montoya, who scalped Governor Charles Bent in front of his family. That revolt in this town involved the siege of Simeon Turley's mill and distillery in Arroyo Hondo as well as the Battles of Mora. The ashes of author (20 pts)",
        "D.H. Lawrence were interred on a ranch in this town, near where he stayed with wealthy patron Mabel Dodge Luhan. Ansel Adams and (10 pts)",
        "Georgia O'Keeffe were associated with an art colony in this town, which takes its name from an almost millennium-old pueblo. For ten points, name this New Mexico town."
      ],
      "answer": "Taos"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Historian William Dalrymple has called this man an “unstable sociopath,\" and in 2020, petitions were signed calling for the removal of a statue of this man on London's King Charles Street. This man took the city of Arcot [[AR-kot]] in 1751 during the Second (20 pts)",
        "Carnatic War to relieve an attack by Joseph-Francois Dupleix [[doo-PLEH]]. This man's policies have been identified as leading to the outbreak of a severe famine in (10 pts)",
        "Bengal in 1770. For ten points, name this man, who led the forces of the British East India Company to victory at the Battle of Plassey."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Robert Clive or 1st Baron Clive",
        "Clive of India"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A magistrate from this historical region named John Hunyadi successfully led the resistance against the Ottomans in the 15th century “Long Campaign.” Michael the Brave, the imperial governor of this region, temporarily united this region with the neighboring (20 pts)",
        "Moldavia and Wallachia [[wuh-LAY-kee-uh]]. The Second Vienna Award gave the Kingdom of Hungary the northern reaches of this (10 pts)",
        "Romanian region. For ten points, name this region which means “across the woods” in Latin."
      ],
      "answer": "Transylvania"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) When once asked if he held a patent, this man replied, “Could you patent the sun?” This man’s postgraduate work under Thomas Francis paved the way for his best known discovery. Julius Youngner was among the members of this man’s research lab at the University of (20 pts)",
        "Pittsburgh. This scientist was tasked with finding new variants of the three known strains of a virus for which he developed a countermeasure improved upon by (10 pts)",
        "Albert Sabin. For ten points, name this American developer of the polio vaccine."
      ],
      "answer": "Jonas Salk 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 8"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author used the example of her first encounter with Sapphire from \"Amos n’ Andy\" to claim that a certain image \"was not the body of desire.” This author refuted Laura Mulvey in a work of film theory which criticized Michel Foucault [[foo- KOH]] and coined the term (20 pts)",
        "“oppositional gaze.” This critic of Daniel Patrick Moynihan claimed that the Black nationalist movement relied on misogyny to further its aims in a work named after a (10 pts)",
        "speech given in Ohio by Sojourner Truth. For ten points, name this feminist author of Ain’t I a Woman."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "bell hooks",
        "Gloria Jean Watkins"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Temirgoy are among the twelve main tribes of these people, who were unified by Inal the Radiant. Grigory Zass called for the use of these people in scientific experiments and helped carry out a campaign against them which is remembered on a day of mourning in (20 pts)",
        "Abkhazia. Cossack troops oversaw the forced deportation of this predominantly Muslim group from a region east of the (10 pts)",
        "Black Sea. For ten points, name this Caucasian ethnic group which was subjected to a nineteenth-century ethnic cleansing."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Circassians",
        "Adyghe",
        "Adige",
        "Çerkesler",
        "Čerkesy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This woman finished fourth in the 1977 Democratic mayoral primary in New York. That election was won by Ed Koch, with whom this woman co-sponsored the first federal gay rights bill, the Equality Act of 1974. This eco-feminist ran on the campaign slogan \"This (20 pts)",
        "woman's place is in the House—the House of Representatives.\" This woman presided over the 1977 National Women's Conference and led Jimmy Carter's (10 pts)",
        "National Advisory Commission for Women. For ten points, name this Representative for New York’s 20th district, nicknamed \"Battling Bella.\""
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Bella Abzug",
        "Battling Bella before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Manuel Yan was one of the survivors of a part of this event called the Pantingan River Massacre. Victims of this event were assembled in Mariveles and Bagac before being forced to their destination at Camp O'Donnell. The leader of this event, (20 pts)",
        "Masaharu Homma, was executed in the Tokyo Trials. This event was followed a month later by the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Corregidor in Manila Bay. For ten points, name this event in which American and Filipino prisoners of war were forced to undergo a brutal \"march.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Bataan Death March 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 8"
    }
  ]
}